Guide to the Max Zaritsky Papers TAM.006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Max Zaritsky Papers
1912-1959
1934-1948
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Zaritsky, Max, 1885-1959
Rand School of Social Science
TAM.006
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Max Zaritsky (1885-1959) was an officer, and sometime president, of two hat industry unions, the Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers' International Union, and its successor, the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union. The papers include correspondence with labor and industry leaders, clippings, manuscripts, minutes, typescripts of radio addresses and speeches, and memorabilia and printed material covering hat industry union affairs, political and Zionist activities of the labor movement, and the conflict between the American Federation of Labor and the newly formed Congress of Industrial Organizations.
Custodial History
Collection was part of the Rand School Archives, which were transferred to the Tamiment Library in 1963 by members of the People's Education Camp Society, Inc. The accession number associated with this collection is 1963.016.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Max Zaritsky (1885-1959) was born Petrikov, Russia, emigrated to the U.S., where in 1907 he joined the Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers' International Union (CHCMW), later becoming its president, and then subsequently, president, until his retirement in 1950, of the United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union (AFL), formed by the 1934 merger of the CHCMW and the United Hatters of North America. Zaritsky was an advocate of labor-management cooperation to promote the hat industry, a founder of the American Labor Party in 1936, and was active in labor Zionist circles, heading both the American Jewish Trade Union Committee for Palestine and the National Committee for a Leon Blum Colony in Palestine.
Sources:
Max Zaritsky at Fifty. The Story of an Aggressive Labor Leadership (1935).
Biographical Dictionary of American Labor (1984).
Labor Unions (1977). Includes historical sketches of the various hat industry unions, pp. 139-144.
Scope and Content Note
The papers include correspondence with labor and industry leaders, clippings, manuscripts, minutes, typescripts of radio addresses and speeches, memorabilia and printed material covering hat industry union affairs, political and Zionist activities of the labor movement, and the conflict between the American Federation of Labor and the newly formed Congress of Industrial Organizations.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Max Zaritsky Papers
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers International Union Records (Tamiment 54)
Separated Material
Several photographs have been separated to the Tamiment Library General Photographs Collection (Photographs 1)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transfer from the Rand School Archives, 1963. The accession number associated with this collection is 1963.016
Correspondence.; Palestine.; Speeches.; Minutes (administrative records); Labor Zionism |z United States.; Manuscripts for publication.; Industrial technicians |x Labor unions |z United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Hat trade |x Labor unions |z United States.; Zaritsky, Max, 1885-1959; Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers' International Union; Blum, Léon, 1872-1950; American Jewish Trade Union Committee for Palestine; National Committee for a Leon Blum Colony in Palestine; United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Rand School of Social Science
- Series 1: Max Zaritsky Papers
  - AFL and the CIO: Statements, Speeches, 1936, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Jewish Trade Union Committee for Palestine, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Jewish Trade Union Committee for Palestine, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Jewish Trade Union Committee for Palestine, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Trade Union Council National Committee for Labor Israel, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Zionist Emergency Council, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Biographies, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: By and About Max Zaritsky, 1930s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fiftieth Birthday Dinner, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hatters Unionism, 1912-1918 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hatters Unionism, 1920s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hatters Unionism, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hatters Unionism, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jewish Affairs: Letters, Misc., 1932-1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Labor Economics: Speeches and Related Material, 1938-1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Labor Law: Addresses and General Views, 1936-1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Committee for a Leon Blum Colony in Palestine, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Committee for a Leon Blum Colony in Palestine, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Recovery Administration: Speeches About, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Palestine: Clippings, Articles, Resolutions, 1935-1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Palestine: Speeches on, 1938-1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Palestine: Trip to, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Political Activities and Endorsements, 1935-1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Presidential Elector (Roosevelt), 1936 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Radio Addresses, 1935-1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Retirement / Convention of Hatters Union, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Saturday Evening Post Article: "Can Labor Prosper Under Free Enterprise?" [Jan 30, 1943], 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Speeches Given at Conventions of Other Labor Unions, 1930-1938 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - To the Industry (Addresses), 1931-1943 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Government Citations and Honors, 1945-1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - William Green Dinner, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - William Green Dinner (American Trade Union Council for Histadrut), 1951 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - World War I: Liberty Loan Committee, Other Fundraising, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - World War II: Addresses, 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 15)